"Groatzempic: Using Intact
Grains to Boost GLP-1"
In my last few videos,
I talked about using prebiotics,
like fiber,
to deliver nutrients
to the colon
for the sustained
and prolonged release
of appetite-reducing
gut hormones like GLP-1.
That’s because the majority
of cells producing GLP-1
are located
at the end of the gut,
in our large intestine.
But prebiotics
don’t represent the only
"slow digestion-oriented
dietary strategy"
to sustain
the secretion of GLP-1.
Prebiotics can be used
to promote metabolic health
and longevity by stimulating
intestinal production of GLP-1,
and so too
can the drug Acarbose,
which acts as a starch blocker,
inhibiting the enzymes
that would normally digest
carbohydrates earlier
in the small intestine.
Acarbose-induced transfer
of carbs to the lower parts
of the intestine
increases GLP-1 levels.
And since changes in GLP-1
correlate with weight loss
in those on the drug,
it’s reasonable to suspect
that GLP-1 is a mediator
of the favorable impact
of acarbose therapy
on weight control.
There’s also a third strategy,
eating "lente" carbohydrates,
from the Latin lentus for slow.
Instead of taking a drug to slow
dietary carbohydrate digestion,
what about just choosing a diet
centered around slow-digesting
"lente" carbohydrates
to achieve comparable benefits?
That’s the theory, anyway.
So, that means pasta,
beans, groats,
meaning structurally intact
grain kernels,
as well as sprouted grains.
Let’s start with beans.
Here, researchers found
enhanced secretion
of satiety-promoting
gut hormones
after the consumption
of white bread
that had been enriched with
coarsely ground chickpea flour,
and the more chickpea
it contained,
the higher
the GLP-1 levels spiked,
but where are you going
to find chickpea bread?
What about just eating beans?
Asking people to eat five cups
(850-900 g) of beans a week
spontaneously led
to health benefits
similar to those seen
after asking people
to cut 500 calories
out of their daily diet,
but there was no change
in GLP-1 levels.
What about cocoa beans?
I wish, but sadly,
no effect of dark chocolate
on GLP-1 either.
The one pasta study I could find
also failed to bump GLP-1,
but the one
sprouted grain study I found
showed higher GLP-1 response
to sprouted bread,
compared to four other types
of bread,
which didn’t differ
significantly from each other.
Eleven- or 12-grain bread
was no different
than white bread?
That’s what’s generally found
when comparing products
made with whole-grain flour
to refined-grain flour;
there aren’t any immediate
right-after-the-meal effects
of whole wheat bread compared
to white bread, for example.
You can’t just eat bread
and expect some kind
of "doughzempic" effect,
because, as I explained
in my last few videos,
food structure is critical
for optimal health.
When grains are milled
into flour,
whether whole wheat or white,
their cell walls are ruptured
and the starch spills out
and never makes it
down to our colon;
so, we don’t get
their added benefit.
This is one of the reasons
former Harvard nutrition chair
Walt Willett
has argued that the term
whole grain
should probably be reserved for
only whole intact grain kernels,
otherwise known as groats,
the "wholiest" of grains.
In my book How Not to Diet,
I talk about my BROL bowl,
a prebiotic mix
that includes barley groats,
rye groats, and oat groats.
What effect might they have
on GLP-1?
If you give people bread
containing some
whole intact barley groats,
there’s no immediate difference
in GLP-1 levels
in the subsequent three hours,
but the groats
wouldn’t even have had time
to make it down to your colon
that quickly.
However,
after your good bacteria
have had a chance
to break open their cell walls,
you get a greater,
higher GLP-1 bump
more than 12 hours later,
at breakfast the next day.
The question, though,
is whether that translates
into a suppressed appetite.
And indeed, lower food intake
not just at breakfast,
but also at lunch the next day,
14 hours later!
Having barley kernels
at an evening meal
not only increased GLP-1
the next day,
boosting blood levels
by 43 percent at breakfast,
but feelings of hunger
decreased
during the entire next day,
and the research participants
ate about 100 fewer calories
of an all-you-can-eat lunch,
just because they had
some barley groats
fourteen hours before.
Eat barley groats
three days in row
and on the fourth day
see a 56 percent increase
in the level of GLP-1
in your blood.
What about rye groats?
Eat rye groats for supper,
and more than 10 hours later,
your GLP-1 levels are up,
and your appetite is down.
Researchers found
that participants
had an increased
subjective feeling of satiety
during the course
of the entire next day.
So, rye groats
"demonstrate anti-diabetes
and anti-obesity potential
as manifested by
enhanced blood sugar control
and increased GLP-1
and the accompanying
appetite suppression."
And there was a correlation
between the short-chain
fatty acids,
acetate and propionate,
and GLP-1 response,
suggesting that, indeed,
we may have
our good gut bugs to thank
for the beneficial effects.